Finding Aid for Thomas M. Spaulding papers, 1901-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas M. Spaulding papers 1901-1969
Spaulding, Thomas M. (Thomas Marshall), 1882-1973.
2 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
8653 Aa 2; Ac
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Thomas M. Spaulding (donor no. 1752 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas Marshall Spaulding, born 1882 in St. Johns, Michigan, was a graduate of the University of Michigan, College of LS&A, 1902. After graduation, he went to West Point where he received his commission as a second lieutenant in 1905. He was a career army officer until 1936 when he retired with the rank of colonel. During the second World War he was called back for a period of active duty as chief of the records division of the adjutant general's office.
Spaulding and his wife Florence had one child Stephen who died while at the University of Michigan in 1925. As a memorial to his son, Spaulding, upon a proposal from University Librarian William Warner Bishop, began to establish a collection of books for the library. The themes of the collection included military history, English local history as well as liturgical tracts and incunabula.
Through his work on the Stephen Spaulding collection, Spaulding became a bibliophile, collecting and writing on military topics, history, bibliography and American biography. He also wrote on the history of the Cosmos Club of which he was a member and in 1952 its president.
Spaulding died April 11, 1973.
The Thomas M. Spaulding collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence and other materials; Biographical and Personal; Organizational Affiliations; Political Materials; Topical Files; Writings; Stephen Tucker Spaulding Materials; and Photographs. The correspondence is of interest for its mention of current affairs, national politics, and the Cosmos Club of Washington, D.C. Of special interest are two volumes of diaries, covering the period of 1941-1944, with detailed comments on the conduct of World War II as viewed from Washington, D.C.
Subjects:
Cosmos Club (Washington, D.C.); Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan State University.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Washington (D.C.); William L. Clements Library.; World War, 1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cosmos Club (Washington, D.C.); Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Great Britain.; Interiors.; Spaulding, Thomas M. (Thomas Marshall), b. 1882.; National Archives (U.S.)
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Beta Theta Pi. Lambda Chapter (University of Michigan); Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Castle, William R. (William Richards), 1878-1963.; Fairbanks, Avard T. (Avard Tennyson), 1897-1987.; Karpinski, Louis Charles, 1878-1956.; Leonard, Irving A. (Irving Albert), 1896-1996.; McAllister, Samuel Wilson, 1890-; McMurtrie, Douglas C. (Douglas Crawford), 1888-1944.; Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.; Peckham, Howard H. (Howard Henry), 1910-1995.; Pratt, Julius William, 1888-; Rice, Warner Grenelle, 1899-; Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Shaw, Wilfred Byron, 1881-1959.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Trevelyan, George Macaulay, 1876-1962.; Vander Velde, Lewis G. (Lewis George), 1890-1975.; Warren, Charles.; Yoakum, Clarence Stone, 1879-1945.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1901-1969, 42 folders (Box 1)
- Biographical and Personal
  - Biographical information (Box 2)
    (see also diplomas, citations, etc. in oversize folder)
  - Military Orders (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1941-1944, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    (The covers of the diaries read 1942 and 1943)
  - U.S. Military Academy class letters, class of 1905 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Organizational affiliations
  - Beta Theta Pi materials (Box 2)
  - Cosmos Club materials (Box 2)
  - Literary Society (Box 2)
- Political materials
  - Republican National Committee, political notes, 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - Taft for President (Robert Taft) material, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Taft-for-President Committee material compiled by Thomas M. Spaulding (Box 2)
- Topical files
  - Hawaii, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - International Sheep Dog Society (Box 2)
  - Military Affairs (Box 2)
  - National Cathedral (Box 2)
  - Rare Books (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Reprints of Writings (Box 2)
  - Drafts of Writings, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Military Science articles by T. M. Spaulding, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Hawaii articles by T. M. Spaulding (Box 2)
  - Washington Cathedral Library articles by T. M. Spaulding (Box 2)
- Stephen Tucker Spaulding
  - The Stephen Spaulding Collection in 1957 (Box 2)
  - Stephen Tucker Spaulding, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 2)
  - Military class (1905) reunions (Box 2)
  - Stephen Tucker Spaulding (Box 2)
  - Cosmos Club (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Library presentation (Box 2)